Pinelands Folklife Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Pinelands Folklife Project collection 1983-1991 1983-1987
AFC 1991/023
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
approximately 31,303 items
26 containers
13 linear feet
approximately 9,500 sheets; 8.5 x 14 in. or smaller
approximately 75 sheets; oversize documents
113 floppy disks: single-sided and double sided; 5 1/4 in.
5 floppy disks; 3 1/2 in.
3 computer tape cartridges (DC 300XL)
247 sound tape reels: analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono.; 5 in., 7 in.
118 sound cassettes: analog
11,793 film negatives: black-and-white; 35 mm
9,205 film transparencies: color; 35 mm
222 film transparencies: color; 2 x 2 in.
11 photographic prints: color; 3.5 x 3.5 in.; 3.5 x 5 in.
4 photographic prints: black-and-white; 3.5 x 5 in.
1 videocassette (VHS) (30 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in.
3 videocassettes (U-Matic) (150 min.): sound, color; 3/4 in.
2 film reels: silent, color; 16 mm
1 t-shirt
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of ethnographic materials gathered by a team of fieldworkers in the mid-1980s to document the cultural traditions of the people inhabiting the Pinelands National Reserve in New Jersey. Sponsored by the American Folklife Center.
Provenance
Accessioned; 1991.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Pinelands Folklife Project collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Maps have not been processed.
Online Content
Part of the Pinelands Folklife Project collection (primarily Series 3) is available on the Library of Congress website at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.afc1991023.
Administrative History
The National Parks and Recreation Act (P.L. 95-625) established the Pinelands National Reserve in 1978 to protect the unique cultural and environmental resources of the Pine Barrens region in southern New Jersey, and the Pinelands Commission, an oversight board made up of federal, state, and local representatives, to develop policies to protect, preserve, and enhance these resources.
In cooperation with the commission, the American Folklife Center undertook the Pinelands Folklife Project to identify and document the various aspects of traditional culture existing within and around the Pinelands National Reserve. The project was intended to test the concepts and recommendations set forth in the report Cultural Conservation: The Protection of Cultural Heritage in the United States, prepared by the American Folklife Center and the Department of the Interior. The inquiry of the field study concentrated on the interplay between the local culture and the natural landscape, and the social construction of place.
The project was executed in three phases between May 1983 and September 1986, which consisted of planning and personnel selection, field research and documentation, and the development of educational products. The project was directed by Mary Hufford, and co-planned by Carl Fleischhauer, of the American Folklife Center. The core team included administrative coordinator Sue Samuelson; three full-time field-workers, Jens Lund, Elaine Thatcher, and Christine Cartwright; and three part-time project associates, Bonnie Blair, Tom Carroll, and Malachi O'Connor. Two additional folklorists from state government agencies contributed to the project: David Cohen of the New Jersey Historical Commission and Rita Moonsammy of the New Jersey State Council on the Arts. Dennis McDonald, of the Burlington County Times newspaper, and Joseph Czarnecki served as project photographers. Eugene Hunn, an ethnobiologist, and Nora Rubinstein, an environmental psychologist, contributed to the project on a consultative basis. The final phase of the project was conducted in cooperation with representatives from the National Park Service, the New Jersey State Historical Commission, the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, and the New Jersey Department of Human Resources.
Scope and Content
The Pinelands Folklife Project collection represents the culmination of a three-year effort to identify and record the cultural traditions of the inhabitants in and around the Pinelands National Reserve in the Pine Barrens region of southern New Jersey in the mid-1980s. The collection comprises ethnographic documentation which examines the relationship between the local culture and the surrounding environment. The collection contains the administrative records, planning documents, and published materials related to the management of the field project. The bulk of the collection consists of field documentation recorded in a range of formats, including typed field notes and logs, sound recordings, graphic materials, moving images, and one artifact. The collection also includes promotional materials, project publications, slide presentations, video programs, and documentation related to the museum exhibition and conference, New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment.
The Pinelands Folklife Project was the first ethnographic study undertaken by the American Folklife Center to use computers in the field, and the computer disks and computer tape cartridges which contain field data and the project database are included as part of the collection. A t-shirt with a design which commemorates the use of computers to manage and execute the project is also included in the collection.
A copy of the final published report, One Space, Many Places: Folklife and Land Use in New Jersey's Pinelands National Reserve, written by project director Mary Hufford, is located in folder number 183 of the collection. A copy of the Inventory to the Pinelands Folklife Project and Geographic Index, prepared by Ann Dancy as a supplement to the final report, is located in the first folder of the collection.
Arrangement
The Pinelands Folklife Project collection is organized into five series:
Series 1: Project administration files
Series 2: Collected publications and ephemera
Series 3: Field documentation arranged by fieldworker
Series 4: Final products
Series 5: Maps of New Jersey Pinelands
Field Project Identifiers and Logs
Photographs, recordings, and their logs are numbered with field project identifiers which codify the creator, format, year, and/or sequence of a given item.
Black-and-white negatives are identified by the year in which the photograph was taken, the letter "B" which identifies the negative as a black-and-white image, the two-letter initials of the fieldworker, the six-digit number assigned by the photographic processing lab, and a one- or two-digit number representing the roll of film. "B" logs identify the subjects depicted in these negatives.
Color transparencies are labeled with the year in which the photograph was taken, the letter "C" which identifies the transparency as a color image, the two-letter initials of the fieldworker, and the sequential number of the roll of film. "C" logs identify the subjects depicted in these transparencies.
Sound recordings are labeled with the year in which the recording was taken, the letter "A" which identifies the recording as an audiocassette or "R" which identifies it as a reel-to-reel tape, the two-letter initial of the fieldworker, and the sequential number of the recording. AFS numbers were later added as additional identifiers for sound recordings. "A" and "R" logs summarize the conversations recorded on the tapes; logs sometimes include transcripts.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carroll, Thomas DeBlasio; Cartwright, Christine A., 1955-1983; Cervetto, Jack, 1908-1995; Cohen, David Steven, 1943-; Czarnecki, Joseph P.; Fleischhauer, Carl; Glassie, Henry, 1941-; Hufford, Mary, 1952-; Hufford, Mary, 1952- One space, many places: folklife and land use in New Jersey's Pinelands National Reserve.; Hunn, Eugene S.; Little, Silas; Lund, Jens, 1946-; McDonald, Dennis, 1954-; Moonsammy, Rita Zorn; Morgan, Elizabeth M.; O'Connor, Bonnie Blair; O'Connor, Malachi; Orr, Jay; Parsons, Gerald E., 1940-1995; Ridgway, Arlene Martin, 1936-; Ridgway, Merce; Rubinstein, Nora J. (Nora Jane); Samuelson, Sue, 1956-1991; Shourds, Harry V.; Sinton, John W.; Thatcher, Elaine; Tweed, Stewart M.; Vivian, V. Eugene.
Organizations
American Folklife Center; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); New Jersey. Pinelands Commission.; Pinehawkers (Musical group); Pinelands Cultural Society.; Pinelands Folklife Project (N.J.)
Subjects
Baptists--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.; Catholics--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.; Conservation of natural resources--New Jersey--Pine Barrens.; Cultural property--Protection--New Jersey--Pine Barrens.; Fishing--New Jersey--Anecdotes.; Folk music--New Jersey.; Hunting--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve--Anecdotes.; Hymns, English--New Jersey.; Italian Americans--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.; Land use--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.; Oystering--New Jersey--Anecdotes.; Puerto Ricans--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.; Sand and gravel mines and mining--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve--Anecdotes.; Ukrainian Americans--New Jersey--Pinelands National Reserve.
Places
Patuxent River Valley (Md.); Pine Barrens (N.J.)--Folklore.; Pine Barrens (N.J.)--Religious life and customs.; Pine Barrens (N.J.)--Social life and customs.; Pinelands National Reserve (N.J.)
Form/Genre
Aerial photographs.; Correspondence.; Field notes.; Field recordings.; Hymns.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Container List
- Series 1: Project administration files
  Summary: Project proposals, budget material, correspondence, personnel information, and public relations information.
  - Pinelands Folklife Project collection guide: finding aid, inventory, geographic index, and summary sheet, April 1989-August 1999 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Meetings, report of initial meeting of participating agencies, report of team meetings (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Plan for mapping subject locations, planning list of categories of investigation (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Proposal and budget (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Pre-fieldwork preparation sheets (Box-folder 21/197 (Oversize))
  - Bank account records--New Jersey (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Budget material--New Jersey field office (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Project budget worksheet (Box-folder 21/197 (Oversize))
  - Fieldworker car rental information (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Computer expenses (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Computer Task Study, notes on media documentation, report and recommendations for micro-computer hardware and software use in the field, system to be used for information storage and retrieval (Box-folder 1/9)
    See also Field Notes, PFP-83-FCC-0917, in Box 21 (oversize storage)
  - Fieldworker invoices (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Record of housing expenses (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Lodging: Lebanon State Forest and New Lisbon State School (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Media documentation, invoices, and purchase orders (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Petty cash receipts--New Jersey field office (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Purchase orders (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Travel expenses (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Summaries of expenditures (Box-folder 2/17)
  - List of fieldworkers, survey orientation document, and outline of fieldworkers' responsibilities (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Advance materials for fieldworkers (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Administrative notes and memos to fieldworkers (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Computer forms and examples for fieldworkers (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Contractual information for fieldworkers (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Blair, Bonnie--Fieldworker, Project Associate (Box-folder 2/23)
    Start-up information, final report
  - Carroll, Tom--Fieldworker, Project Associate (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Cartwright, Christine--Fieldworker (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Czarnecki, Joseph--Photographer (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Czarnecki, Joseph--Photographer (Box-folder 21/200 (Oversize))
    Sabatini, Arthur J. He Photographed the Ferment in Poland. March 16-30, 1983
    DeSantis, Tullio Francesco. Shots Seen 'Round the World. March 27, 1983
    Poland through the Lens of Joseph Czarnecki. The Polish Review. March 24-30, 1983 (with translation)
  - Hunn, Eugene S.--Consultant, Ethnobiologist (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Lund, Jens--Fieldworker (Box-folder 2/28)
  - O'Connor, Malachi Sheehan--Fieldworker, Project Associate (Box-folder 2/29)
    Start-up information, personnel file, final report
  - Rubinstein, Nora Jane--Consultant, Environmental Psychologist (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Samuelson, Sue--Administrative Coordinator (Box-folder 3/31)
  - Thatcher, Elaine--Fieldworker (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Glassie, Henry--Consultant (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Correspondence re: Christine Cartwright (Box-folder 3/34)
    Includes 1 color photographic print (3.5 x 5 inches)
  - Correspondence with informants, includes certificates of appreciation (Box-folder 3/35)
    Includes 5 color photographic prints (approximately 3.5 x 3.5 inches) by Harry Shourds
  - Correspondence--Pinelands Commission (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Team correspondence (Box-folder 3/37)
  - Third party correspondence, 1983 to 1986 (Box-folder 3/38)
  - Correspondence -- Congressional (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Correspondence -- Mayors and governors (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Publicity and public relations, 1983 (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Publicity and public relations, 1984 to 1985 (Box-folder 3/42)
  - Publicity clipping: Jersey Blues (Box-folder 21/199 (Oversize))
    Color original newspaper clipping and preservation photocopy
  - UNIX BRS search-and-retrieval software, March 25, 1987, 12 computer disks (5.25 inch, double sided) (Box 28)
  - Pinelands Folklife Project Archive in Fortune Word (fieldworker documentation), circa March 1986, 16 computer disks (5.25 inch) (Box 28)
  - Original PINY conversion to ASCII, backed up with Norton Backup, June 7, 1991, 5 computer disks (3.5 inch) (Box 28)
  - PINY backup in BRS and "Redirect" ASCII files, January 14 to 15, 1991, 3 computer tape cartridges (DC 300XL) (Box 28)
  - Backup copies of PINY document/file information, BRS Search-and-retrieval software, and Pineland Folklife Project Archive in Fortune Word, April 10, 1986 to July 10, 1987, 85 computer disks (5.25 inch) (Box 29)
  - Pinelands Folklife Project T-shirt, AFC 1991/023: AR001; 1 T-shirt (Box 30)
- Series 2: Collected publications and ephemera, Materials listed in this series are manuscripts, books, periodicals, articles, news clippings, and photocopies, unless otherwise noted. Dates in this series refer to date of publication. This series includes additional publications not listed here.
  Summary: Pamphlets, articles, books, reports, and government publications describing the history, culture, and environment of the Pinelands National Reserve.
  - Pinelands legislation (Box-folder 4/43)
  - New Jersey Pinelands Comprehensive Management Plan (Box-folder 4/44)
    See also New Jersey Pinelands land use map in Map Cabinet Drawer 20
  - Berger, Jonathan. Planning the Use and Management of the Pinelands: A Report for the New Jersey Pinelands Commission, February 15, 1980 (Box-folder 4/45)
  - Municipal master plans for Bass River Township, Medford, Evesham, Tabernacle (Box-folder 5/46)
    See also Evesham Township, Burlington County, New Jersey land use maps in Map Cabinet Drawer 20
  - Township of Tabernacle, Burlington County, New Jersey Master Plan Program, July 1982 (Box-folder 21/194 (Oversize))
  - Resolution to adopt Hamilton Township master plan booklet (Box-folder 5/46)
  - Agenda from Pinelands Commission meeting (Box-folder 5/46)
  - Public relations brochures: Burlington Co., Egg Harbor, Jackson Township, Manchester Township, Pemberton Township, Smithville, Fort Dix (Box-folder 5/47)
  - Pinelands Commission information packet, 1982 to 1985 (Box-folder 5/48)
    Educational and promotional materials; sample Pinelands Commission newsletters; several issues of The Pinelander newsletter
  - Buchholz, Kenneth, and Ralph E. Good. Compendium of Archaeological, Cultural, and Historical Literature of the New Jersey Pine Barrens, July 1983 (Box-folder 6/49)
  - Buchholz, Kenneth, and Ralph E. Good. Compendium of New Jersey Pine Barrens Literature, July 1982 (Box-folder 6/50)
  - Good, Ralph E. Ecological Solutions to Environmental Management Concerns in the Pinelands National Reserve, December 1982 (Box-folder 6/51)
  - Roman, Charles T., and Ralph E. Good. Wetlands of the New Jersey Pinelands: Values, Functions, Impacts and a Proposed Buffer Delineation Model, 1983 (Box-folder 6/51)
  - Berger, Jonathon. Untitled dissertation on landscape planning, 1984 (Box-folder 6/52)
  - Berger, Jonathan. Landscape Patterns of Local Social Organization and Their Importance for Land Use and Social Planning (photocopy), 1981 (Box-folder 6/52)
  - Goldstein, Joan. Environmental Decision Making in Rural Locales: The Pine Barrens, 1981 (Box-folder 6/53)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper and magazine articles on Pinelands preservation issues (Box-folder 7/54)
  - Materials on categories of public land use (Box-folder 7/55)
  - Pinelands maps, miscellaneous maps, and promotional materials (Box-folder 7/56)
  - Articles and pamphlets about the Pine Barrens (Box-folder 7/57)
  - Folklife materials and the interpretation of folklife in US national parks (not including the Pinelands National Reserve) (Box-folder 7/58)
  - National Park Service. Glassberg, David. Various planning documents pertaining to cultural resource management and interpretation in the Pinelands National Reserve (Box-folder 7/59)
  - National Park Service. The New Jersey Pinelands: A Progress Report on the Nation's First National Reserve (draft), March 1983 (Box-folder 7/60)
  - Stephenson, S. N. Vegetation Change in the Pine Barrens of New Jersey in The Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club (photocopy), March 1965 to April 1965 (Box-folder 7/62)
  - McCormick, Jack. The Pine Barrens: Vegetation Geography, 1973, Missing (Box-folder 7/63)
  - Partial List of Sources for Plant Material Indigenous to Pinelands Area, 1981 to 1982 (Box-folder 7/64)
  - Natural Resources Inventory, Borough of Chesilhurst, 1982 (Box-folder 7/65)
  - Wacker, Peter. Human Exploitation of the Pine Barrens Before 1900 (photocopy), 1979 (Box-folder 7/66)
  - Stephenson, S. N. Vegetation Change in the Pine Barrens of New Jersey in The Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club (photocopy), 1979 (Box-folder 7/66)
  - Wacker, Peter. Cultural Geography of Eighteenth Century New Jersey in the New Jersey's Revolutionary Experience series (photocopy), 1975 (Box-folder 7/66)
  - Historical articles and information about the cranberry/blueberry industry (Box-folder 8/67)
  - Truck farming material (Box-folder 8/68)
  - Materials pertaining to regulation of fishing, hunting, and trapping (Box-folder 8/69)
  - Sinton, John, ed. Natural and Cultural Resources of the New Jersey Pine Barrens, 1978 (Box-folder 8/70)
  - Sinton, John, ed. History, Culture, and Archaeology of the New Jersey Pine Barrens: Essays from the third Pine Barrens Conference, 1981 (Box-folder 8/71)
  - New Jersey and National Registers of Historic Places; Historical Sites of the New Jersey Pinelands (Box-folder 8/72)
  - Sinton, John Walter. An Inventory of Historic and Cultural Resources of the New Jersey Pinelands, prepared for the Pinelands Commission, 1980 (Box-folder 8/73)
  - Pinelands Cultural Resource Management Plan for Historic Period Sites, prepared for the Pinelands Commission, March 1986 (Box-folder 9/74)
  - Pinelands Cultural Resource Management Plan for Historic Period Sites, prepared for the Pinelands Commission, revised April 1991 (Box-folder 9/74)
  - Pinelands Commission cultural resource review process; guidelines for cultural resource surveys; sample reports; outlines; procedures (Box-folder 9/75)
    See also Township of Medford, County of Burlington, New Jersey Sketch plan in Map Cabinet Drawer 20
  - National Park Service. Vernacular residential architecture in the Pinelands National Reserve: A Preliminary assessment, 1983 (Box-folder 9/76)
  - Collection of site descriptions from the New Jersey Historic Preservation Architecture Survey, 1983 (Box-folder 9/76)
  - Boucher, Jack. Domestic Architecture of New Jersey in Antiques (photocopy), July 1965 (Box-folder 9/76)
  - Bolger, William, et al. Historic Architectural Survey and Preservation Planning Project: Village of Whitesbog, September 1982 (Box-folder 9/77)
  - Whitesbog Village Preservation News, vol. 1 no. 1, December 15, 1983 (Box-folder 9/77)
  - Articles on local history, genealogy, culture, and folklore from three southern New Jersey periodicals (Box-folder 10/78)
  - National Park Service summary of Elizabeth Marsh's Feburary 1983 report Scenic Preference (Box-folder 10/79)
  - Rubinstein, Nora Jane. A psycho-social impact analysis of environmental change in New Jersey's Pine Barrens (excerpt), 1983 (Box-folder 10/80)
  - USGS. The National Gazetteer of the United States of America: New Jersey, 1982 (Box-folder 10/81)
  - Miscellaneous USGS information and photocopied news clippings (Box-folder 10/81)
  - New Jersey Field Recordings in the Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. (Box-folder 10/82)
  - Articles on music in the Pine Barrens (Box-folder 10/82)
    Includes 1 color photographic print (approximately 3.5 x 3.5 inches) depicting an unidentified string instrument band
  - Farm Security Administration & Office of War Information collection, Prints and Photographs Division, Library of Congress: Collection profile (Box-folder 10/83)
  - Farm Security Administration & Office of War Information collection, Prints and Photographs Division, Library of Congress: Copies of prints (Box-folder 21/196 (Oversize))
  - Library of Congress reproduction information (Box-folder 10/83)
  - Articles on Pine Barrens folk culture published in New Jersey Folklore before the Pinelands Folklife Project, before 1983 (Box-folder 10/84)
  - Halpert, Herbert. Folktales and legends from the New Jersey pines: a collection and a study, 1947, Missing (Box-folder 10/85)
  - Articles on the Jersey Devil (Box-folder 10/86)
    See also Folder 84, Articles on Pine Barrens folk culture published in New Jersey Folklore
  - Newspaper and magazine articles on the Barnegat Bay sneakbox (Box-folder 10/87)
  - In The Barnegat Bay Tradition, May 18, 1988, AFC 1991/023: MV01; VAP 3372; 1 VHS videocassette (30 minute): sd., color
    In The Barnegat Bay Tradition, produced in 1982 by the New Jersey Network and the New Jersey Historical Commission's Folklife Program, documents the traditions of sneakbox boat building and decoy carving in Barnegat Bay, New Jersey. Includes interviews with Sam Hunt, sneakbox boat builder, Harry V. Shoares, carver of duck decoys, and John Hillman, collector of decoys.
  - Newspaper and magazine articles on hunting, trapping, gathering, shell fishing, etc. (Box-folder 10/88)
  - Folk-Artists-in-Education materials, Bayville and Cumberland County (Box-folder 10/89)
  - Pinelands Folk Festival, AFC 1991/023: MV03-04; VBV 5735-5736; 2 Umatic videocassettes (60 minute): sd., color; Shot log available
    Pinelands Folk Festival, a four-part program produced by Clear Television Cable Corporation, documents the Pinewald Folk Festival at Central Regional High School in Bayville, New Jersey. The program includes interviews with participants and organizers of the event.
  - Miscellaneous student projects (Box-folder 10/90)